I'm very susceptible to location
and to artifacts.
When I started films as a young man,
I could, say, see a ruined
sort of building or something
and imagine all kinds of things
happening in it.
I could think of little films to make in it.
And it itself would contain a story in a way,
like a mystery.
So when I first walked
into the hall at St. Andrew's,
in fact many of their rooms there,
I was, you know, provoked
and stimulated by them
and was thinking of which scenes
I could stage where.
You know, the mood that was there.
And the feeling, I think, left
from all of the energies and emotions
of young people passing
through the school,
you know, during its lifetime
were palpable.
And then I like props. You know,
I like the bagpipes being assembled.
You know, it's like sort of equipment
that's tactile.
You know, these are precious artifacts
of the school.
Sacred things, you know,
the candle, the banners.
You know, this is ritual.
So I thought that this was
the way to begin the film,
was really to take the audience
in a way
through what I had experienced
in visiting the school.
And what I experienced
all those years ago as a young man
in Bellevue Hill in Sydney going
from my first day to the Scots College
where... You know, I wish we could smell
the things you smell.
The smell of oiled wood.
The smell of old leather,
and dust and books and...
These are memories deeply rooted in us
from our school days.
I mean, everybody's school days
is something,
whether it was good, bad
or plain boring, you know?
It's very powerfully imprinted upon you
because it was-
You know, you left home
and left Mom or Dad, or both.
Then you walked through the doors
to what, you don't know.
And how will you go? How will you be?
It's a mystery.
Ladies and gentlemen, boys,
the light of knowledge.
I'm Tom Schulman.
I wrote Dead Poets Society.
I went to a place called Montgomery Bell
Academy for high school,
and I think it was gentleman,
scholar, athlete, Christian.
That was the-
And I wasn't a Christian
so I was gonna miss on that score
right away.
And there was that constant
sort of drumming of those values
into our daily, you know, education.
Tradition, honor,
discipline, excellence.
You could take them
seriously or not, but most people did, so...
And if you didn't, you'd get demerits,
and it was that kind of environment.
I didn't go to a boarding school,
but a lot of people
who worked on this movie,
Peter Weir, Robin Williams did.
So they brought
some of their boarding school experiences
to the movie in various ways.
The school I went to
was an all-boys school
that sort of wished
it could be a boarding school.
So I knew, you know,
that we got our lectures
about what the school should be like
if it could have been
the way they wanted it to be, so...
But I was in high school
in the late '60s
so, you know, the cat was sort of
out of the bag in terms of tradition.
But I certainly understood
the constriction of tradition.
You know, the notion
that if we have to do things
the way we've always done them
simply because
that's the way we do them.
I think as a kid, I felt very- Or as a boy,
I felt very suffocated by that notion
and was glad to see
the '60s rebellion take place.
But given that that was an essential part
of the movie too...
I mean, it's the essential background
of the piece,
that these boys are-
They start out in a place
with the four pillars.
Tradition, honor,
those kinds of things,
which are admirable things but
there can be too much of anything, so...
I'm glad you could come by.
- Thrilling ceremony as usual, Dr. Nolan.
- You've been away too long.
I'd never- I'm not one really for nostalgia
and I'd never thought back
to my school days with fondness
or written some kind of a memoir
or referred to it in any way really. It was-
As soon as the gates were open
in the last year, I ran out of there.
I was glad to get out of there.
But here was the story of school
and a school in the past.
So the first thing I did,
it didn't bother Tom Schulman,
was to just adjust it a few years.
Just earlier, at the end
of the Eisenhower period.
And also the period
in which I was at school.
So I could easily contact the age group
through my memory.
And so I thought of my friends
at school.
I thought of Alex and I thought of Costa
and Mel, you know, and Willy Williams.
So I could put these people together
and imagine
if we were in this circumstance,
because we were
at a very similar school.
The Scots College at Bellevue Hill
which had dayboys, which I was,
and boarders.
You know, very, very strict-
You know, canings,
which you call paddling, and...
I was always getting into trouble there,
you know, and getting whacked,
and, you know,
sort of very much that feeling of-
Like, our motto was:
Utinam Patribus Nostris Digni Simus.
"May we be worthy of our forefathers, "
which we always used to laugh about,
you know?
But that was the atmosphere,
so I could really plug back into it.
And to a degree,
draw on it.
you did summer school.
Yep. Chemistry.
My father thought I should get ahead.
- How was your summer, Slick?
- Keen.
- Meeks, door, closed.
- Yes, sir.
Gentlemen, what are the four pillars?
Travesty, horror,
decadence, excrement.
I'm John Seale
and I was the director of photography
on Dead Poets Society.
It was a project that Peter loved dearly
when he read it.
There was no- There was no way
that he was in any way
not very excited about almost everything
that happened in it.
So that I found in Peter at that stage
was most exciting for me as well,
because everything we talked of,
he was, like, really fired up on it.
It... He related to the kids in the film
and their characters.
Particularly
Tommy Leonard's character.
Even... You know,
even though in that character, the...
His demise towards the end
is very sad in the film,
but he related to his character
with his father relationship.
And he was so excited about all of that
that, you know,
he hated not shooting on Sundays,
which worried us.
Six days is enough, thanks.
But that's how excited he was
about the film.
So the preproduction into it
was a very...
Much more in-depth in a way
of the script.
It's hard to explain that,
but he really went into the script
very deeply.
- Don't ever dispute me in public.
- Father, I wasn't...
After you've finished medical school
and you're on your own,
then you can do as you damn well please,
but until then, you do as I tell you.
- That clear?
- Yes, sir, I'm sorry.
Ahem. You know how much this means
to your mother, don't you?
Yes, sir.
You know me,
always taking on too much.
I think I really worked
pretty much from intuition
in terms of sort of things
outside the actual craft of what I'm doing.
I fundamentally think filmmaking
is a craft.
Film directing.
And just a few individuals are just
a cut above the craft, you know,
or every now and again
are inspired in one way or another.
But then can slump back down in.
No one's brilliant all the time.
I mean, a few freaks of nature
like Mozart or someone.
You know,
even Shakespeare wrote bad plays.
Therefore, you're concentrating
on your craft a lot- Most of the time.
You know, how to get the scene right,
you know, and how to craft it.
It's all conscious.
Good writing, you know, and so forth.
Then there's the other.
There's the other mysterious side,
the unconscious side.
The "I don't know why,
but I think you should do this, " you know?
"Let's go outside.
Let's not do this scene in here. "
Things that become inspirations
so that people remember.
Things that become critical to the film.
And if there's enough of them,
that can, you know,
then jolt the whole thing up
another level.
Small things like the birds.
You know, I filmed those clouds of birds
because they were just there every day.
I used to say,
"What are those birds doing?"
They'd say, "That's the crop.
We've just picked the crop. "
You couldn't look at them
without thinking about it.
What makes them turn when they turn?
You know?
Is there a leader?
Is there a sound, a signal?
You know, so you shoot it.
You sort of think
it's rather like a bunch of these young kids
running around.
You know, they're there at the moment.
Not found their individuality,
like the birds there.
They're just- It's kind of a metaphor.
And then I think,
"Maybe it'll be too obvious. "
And I think,
"Well, we'll see in the cutting room. "
- three laboratory experiments
from the project list
and report on them every five weeks.
We tried very hard not to create
an "evil teachers versus good students"
sort of world.
We tried to set up the parents
and the teachers
and the administration of the school
as people
who were simply doing their jobs
in the way they believe
they should be done,
and parents who were raising their kids
the way it was done at the time
and the way that they believed
it should be done.
So they were true to what it was like then,
you know?
At least that was...
That's my impression of it.
Because I look at them and think,
"Yeah, that's the way it was, " you know?
Nowadays, we look at those people
as though they have some sort of
ulterior motive.
But in fact they were just doing
what they knew how to do best,
you know,
and were teaching and educating
the way they believed it should be done.
This scene, as I recall, originally-
In the original script...
And we shot it, we tried it.
- Keating walked into class
and immediately jumped up on his desk,
and started with some of the-
His dialogue
that's now in the trophy room scene.
And it didn't seem to work.
It was too much. He was kind of
coming too hard at the boys.
So we came up with this idea
that he would just simply walk in
and walk out,
and there would be more mystery
that way
and they would follow him
to the trophy room.
Well, come on.
Tom Schulman's script
was extremely good.
And Peter, like any good director,
would always try to improve it,
has to be the word.
And by doing that we would go
through very carefully every scene
and where it's at in the film.
Should it be there?
Or should it be a little earlier?
Would it explain certain things better
if the scene was placed a little earlier
or even a little later than where Tom
had placed it in the script?
Very in-depth, like, in dissecting
all of the characters and the scenes
to make them all fit and flow,
and to make everything work
towards the end result of the film.
Not a clue?
I often say to writers that, you know,
I sort of have to consume the script
in some way
and make it part of my sensibility.
It has to become organic to me
in a way.
But that's not to take the shine off
what the writer has done,
like as Tom has done with Dead Poets.
It was just damn good writing.
So I think probably what I did
was to edit it somewhat.
And the tone changes then are really
to do only with casting,
which is pretty impactful.
Now,
Mr. Pitts.
Casting's so important.
You know, I think after the concept
or the idea comes casting.
Then comes script, if you're doing
some sort of order of importance,
which is why some people's first films
can be very rough in the script
but if the idea is strong or truthful
and the casting's right,
you know, they'll get a long way with it.
So casting, I love it.
It's exhausting but I do adore it.
Sometimes I think of myself
more like a detective
who's looking for a missing person.
The missing person could be any one
of these people coming in here.
Disguised as it were, you know?
So I'm looking for the character
of John Finch, you know, or somebody.
You're looking
for whatever the character is
and in come a range of people
claiming to be this person.
So as the detective,
I have to thoroughly, you know,
use my intuition and my experience
to work out who is really the person
out of these impostors.
No. Ding.
Thanks for playing anyway.
Because we are food for worms, lads.
Because, believe it or not,
each and every one of us in this room...
I'm very fond of this scene in the hall.
I like how everybody did it.
I don't seem to remember
doing anything.
I remember being there.
But it just-
Everything came together
in the right way for that scene.
The photographs for example,
which were all, you know, obviously real,
that are in the cases.
They seem to me to be-
For every one of our boys,
a face in the photographs
that was almost identical.
That was sheerly by chance.
But, you know, I can... I can see Neil,
I can certainly see Todd in there.
And so I think Robin, who I think
the kind of quality of his voice there
was just right.
The shading and modulation of his voice
is very effective.
Because he's not playing
on obvious emotions. He's not-
You know, the boys
wouldn't accept it anyway if he was.
He's sort of really a rather good storyteller
or a mood-invoker in that scene.
He gets you in, in other words.
Well, you know.
All except one.
And we need always the one
who doesn't get taken in by it,
and thinks he's pretty much a weirdo.
It helped, I think, create a certain magic
to the moment
where they're looking
at those old photographs.
And there are those boys whispering,
you know, back to him, "Carpe diem. "
That just to me created a certain magic.
But this scene
was actually suggested to me
by my next-door neighbor
when I was 12 years old.
I had a...
My next-door neighbor was a guy
who was about three or four years
older than me named Jerry Small, and-
Great guy who when-
We had a brand-new high school
at the time.
And he mentioned to me
that one of the biggest problems
with the high school
was that you wouldn't get trophy cases
with all the pictures and the trophies
because it was a new school
and it had no history.
And then I think he mentioned to me,
he said, "Have you ever looked
at those pictures of those old...?
Old pictures. Those people staring at you,
they're all dead.
They're dead. " You know?
And that always stuck with me,
and that's where this idea, you know,
sort of wove itself into this scene.
- What?
- I can't make it, guys.
I have to have dinner
at the Danburrys' house tonight.
Is there anything worse
than a period film...?
You know, say, you're in this 15th century
and some character goes-
You know, sort of shampooed hair,
sort of flicks, you know.
I wanted to get their hair cut first.
Like the Army, you know?
Big difference to get a haircut.
Haircuts early
and wear their uniforms around quite a bit
and forbidden slang words,
forbidden expressions, you know?
You couldn't say, you know,
"Whatever. It's cool" or "Wow"
or, "Hey, man, " you know, "Shit, "
or anything like that. All banned words.
And then I had researched on which
of the words that were around at the time.
You know, "keeno," I remember
we discovered and something else.
You know, so there was a list of words
that were slang at the time.
And I said, "Above all, you know,
try to, you know,
get into the way of a certain... "
It's awful to say.
"A certain innocence that's gone.
A certain lack of complexity
in young people. "
There wasn't as much- There were good
and bad people, I'm not saying that.
But there wasn't as much
sort of complexity in communication,
or there were no drugs, you know?
So you more fully expressed yourself.
"I don't want anyone, " I said, "to leave
their sentence unfinished like today. "
Like today you can say,
"Oh, man, you know-
Wow, I saw this movie it was-
You know, I mean...
You know, I'm... Wow. "
You know,
so they didn't do that in 1959.
They'd say, "I saw this film last night.
This picture, well, it was really great,
you know?
It was... It's... Cary Grant's in it.
You gotta go and see it. It's wonderful.
I'll go with you again if you wanna go. "
Full sentences
and full, expressed meanings.
And it was all in the spirit of fun,
but it did begin to take effect.
I said, "Try and construct back-stories
with each other. "
I think I said, "Talk to each other about,
you know,
you've been at the school
this period of time. "
Logical things these were,
but, you know,
we had the time to do it over there.
Then I think we had a couple of days
of classrooms
in which I was... Played a teacher.
And I was an English teacher.
I thought it was like a way
of deconstructing my own
position as director to relax everything.
I called myself Mr. Quern.
And I told them
they had to report in uniform
in one of the rehearsal-type spaces.
You know, at 3 p. m. We had desks set up.
Just the key boys.
They came in
and I said, "Okay, sit down. "
I called them their character names.
And I said, "I'm Mr. Quern.
I'm your English teacher this term.
As you know, one of our first priorities
will be to organize the school play.
To which extent, I'm thinking we should
do something original. Any ideas?"
You know,
so they could then react in character.
To a teacher that's not in the script,
you know,
so it wouldn't ruin any of their things.
And I made a fool of myself.
I became an actor myself.
And, you know, I don't say bonded,
I'm sick of that word.
But we just had a good time together
and fun together. And they could explore
their characters a bit.
And we did invent a sort of school play.
And I spoke to them quite seriously,
so if they'd start to giggle, you know,
I'd say, "It's not a laughing matter. "
Then it'd be a strange metaphor.
"We've got a job to do.
Do you understand what I'm saying,
Neil?
Now, let's keep the laughter
for after-hours, all right?
We've got a play to produce
and we've gotta get on with it. "
You know, at the same time being a kind
of a jerk. It's quite complicated.
But it became a sort of... I don't know,
a sort of preliminary story.
We lived that little life
and so by the time we get onto the set
for the first day of shooting,
I'm not the director
but I'm also Mr. Quern.
You know, that's a secret
that they share, you know.
I don't mean
I kept the Mr. Quern thing going,
but everything was alive and crackling.
Mr. Perry, will you read
the opening paragraph of the preface,
entitled "Understanding Poetry"?
"Understanding Poetry,
by Dr. J. Evans Pritchard, Ph. D.
To fully understand poetry,
we must first be fluent with its meter,
rhyme and figures of speech,
then ask two questions.
One: How artfully has the objective
of the poem been rendered?
And two:
How important is that objective?
Question one rates
the poem's perfection.
Question two rates its importance.
And once these questions
have been answered,
determining the poem's greatness
becomes a relatively simple matter.
If the poem's score for perfection
is plotted on the horizontal of a graph,
and its importance
is plotted on the vertical... "
Oddly enough, the draft
that I circulated was the first draft.
It's very rare that I do that. But this...
Most scripts, I'll write 25 or 30- You know,
25 or 30 sets of revisions anyway.
But this one,
I read it over again and again
and I thought- You know, making
little changes but nothing major, so...
But after that,
because we went through two directors,
there were all kinds of little things,
you know?
yielding a massive total area...
When Peter came on, he said,
"Go back to the original
and work off that. "
So... And then it was really that
that kind of...
And then there were-
I think there were three sets
of revisions before shooting.
And in fact,
we only read the script aloud once,
the night before we started shooting.
He had a little read-around with the boys.
And...
Which... And no rehearsals
that I can remember.
Peter liked to basically
shoot the rehearsal, and...
You know,
I remember after the read-around,
I went back in my room
and just wrote all night,
making all kinds of changes.
And without even Peter saying anything,
I just...
I came back and he said,
"What have you done?"
I said, "I've made all these... "
He said, "Why'd you do all that?"
I said, "It's not working. " He's going,
"Oh, don't be ridiculous. It's working. "
Because I don't think I was quite aware
of how to deal with the first reading
and that low level of, you know, energy.
Yeah, that the actors are putting in, so-
Or not putting in, and rightfully so.
You don't want them jumping into their
characters, you know, on the first reading.
It's something they kind of build into.
It's not the Stanislavsky way anyway.
The Method says read it flat.
Let yourself
sort of be filled with the character.
Don't invest the character.
Use the reading
and all the early rehearsals
as a time of exploration.
Let the material work on you.
Don't work on the material.
Rip, rip, rip.
Rip it out. Rip.
Rip, rip.
Yeah.
Rip it out.
What the hell is going on here?
I don't hear enough rips.
- Mr. Keating.
- Mr. McAllister.
I went to university.
You can see me wriggling.
You know, I'm wriggling like this
because I'm thinking, "University. "
You know, I was a real burnout.
You know, I was gone in a year and a bit.
And I'm sure they said good riddance,
you know?
Which is what I said about them,
you know? But I...
I was doing an arts course there.
Once, I had this bad experience
with a poem. It was a Blake poem.
And we'd been asked to read it
for the tutorial.
And to come in
with something prepared on it.
And so it was-
I can't remember the poem.
Maybe it was "The Rose" of Blake's.
I can't remember.
But I do remember everything else.
I remember sitting down.
I was maybe 15 or so.
At Sydney University, I was 18, 19.
And I had loved this poem.
I had just... It filled me. I just loved it.
Maybe four verses.
So the lecturer down the front
in the right lecture theater
wrote it in the blackboard.
And I can still hear this chalk squeaking,
you know, as he wrote out the poem.
Then he sort of dusted his hands off
and turned to us and said,
"Now, this is an inferior poem of Blake's.
Why is it inferior? Let's take a look.
And then we'll hear from you, "
you know?
I began to blush, you know,
because I thought it was so good.
And he then pointed out, you know,
sort of rather poor sort of structure
and, you know,
whatever metaphor was rather obvious.
Banality of its sentiment.
And I looked around at everybody else
who was writing all of this down,
you know?
And I was beet red by this time...
Not that anyone could see me.
- with embarrassment
at my love of the poem.
And that I must be a fool, you know?
And so I left that lecture
and never went back, really.
I just... I never read poetry.
I didn't read poetry for,
I don't know,
maybe till this script came to me.
It'd almost make me nauseous,
you know, to read it.
So that's how bad education can be.
A lot of people
should leave school earlier.
I think it'd probably be better
to get into a trade.
Make shoes or something.
You know, something good like that.
Cook, go to restaurants.
You know, make a different kind of life
based on craft.
I think there's a lot of unhappy people
in college,
who feel that their mom and dad
want you to go there
and that's what you gotta do.
Everybody does it, you know.
Couldn't really care. Just get a grade.
You know? I mean,
I don't really think we're educated
in the way that I think of education
or came to realize education,
you know, could be.
You know, when you read about it,
really kind of my ideal would be,
I suppose,
to have, you know,
gone through the English system
as it was in the late 19th century
or something.
You know, to read history,
as they say.
I think you got a...
You get a good smattering at school.
I think we tend to turn it
into a kind of religion.
You know, it's a—
Or a means to an end, which is—
It's sad in one way. I mean, it's really,
you know, not just-
You know, something
you do in order that you get a good job,
to get a lot of money to go on holiday,
you know, in Florida.
You know, I mean, if that's all the reason,
I'll just keep dancing, you know?
The joy of education is surely
to give you the tools to communicate,
to handle yourself in the world
and to read on.
Read on, you know.
So that you go into your life
and you can,
with all your troubles, you know,
whatever is bothering you
in the world or personally...
You can take a book,
and as they say,
curl up with it, you know?
I don't think there's anything
quite like it for-
There is— Of course, any of the arts
do that. You know, they give you a—
You know, take you out of yourself
and it can be anywhere from ecstasy.
You know, as a way to— To simply
engaging your intellect or emotion.
Captain of the soccer team,
editor of the school annual,
Cambridge bound,
thigh man, and the Dead Poets Society.
"Man most likely to do anything. "
Thigh man. Mr. К was a hell-raiser.
- What's the Dead Poets Society?
- Is there a picture?
- Nothing, no other mention of it.
- That boy there, see me after lunch.
Mr. Keating.
Sir?
Say something.
О Captain, My Captain?
Gentlemen.
We were just looking in your old annual.
Oh, my God.
No, that's not me.
Stanley "The Tool" Wilson.
You know, that film was shot
before the innovation of monitors
on the set.
So it was shot in what I think
I can call the old-fashioned way
where the director would talk
to the operator or the DP
and I was doing both there,
which I love doing with Peter, of course.
And, you know, a lot of the preproduction
we did have certain shots
and certain movements of the camera
predetermined,
but a lot of the time it was what we used
to call the "what if" system.
What if we do that? What if we do this?
Which is all part of simply being ready
to convert to whatever the situation
will give us or the actor would give us.
And I remember one was a long-
A particularly long dolly
was the one that we set up
where the boys walk out to see Keating.
And then they run back in excitement.
And I remembered as the operator,
the value of reading,
and in fact learning, the script
because the light was failing.
And I remember being very angst
about that, that we're losing the light.
We didn't wanna come back the next day.
We had a schedule. And Peter said:
"I want the boys to really run back.
They're excited.
Now they're gonna run back
and start the Dead Poets Society
and go to the cave and-"
But they were throwing lines as they ran
and the dolly's rattling away
and three or four guys pulling it.
And I remembered thinking, you know,
that I've only got a couple of takes of this
and then the light'll be gone.
And the value of reading the script deeply
enough to almost learn the lines
meant that I could anticipate
who was gonna talk next.
And I was able to whip pan to them.
Get their line, then whip pan
to the next guy.
And we got it.
And I think that was, you know,
like an instance of, you know,
this speed we have to maintain.
But the weather,
you know, the night falling
simply meant that it tightened
the noose on us
to get it right the first time
or the second time.
Move.
- Me too.
-1 don't know, Neil.
What? Pitts.
- Pittsie, come on.
- His grades are hurting.
- You can help him, Meeks.
- What is this, a midnight study group?
Forget it, you're coming.
Meeks, your grades hurting too?
- I'll try anything once.
- Except sex.
I'm in as long as we're careful.
- What about you, Knox?
- I don't know, Charlie.
Come on, Knox. It'll help you get Chris.
Yeah? How?
- Women swoon. Ha, ha, ha.
- But why do they swoon?
Charlie, tell me why they swoon.
Charlie.
You're not listening.
Look, you follow the stream
to the waterfall.
It's right there. It's gotta be like-
I grew up
in the mythological South, you know?
I grew up in the real South.
And there were a lot of little secret
and not so secret societies in the South
when I grew up there.
Every high school would have three
or four or five fraternities and sororities.
Some of them were citywide.
Some of them,
as far as I know, were national.
So there were these clubs
that you were either in or out of,
and all that sort of thing going on, but-
So sort of being a part of it, you know,
conforming, being cool
was very important, you know.
And how that plays into
the Dead Poets Society,
to that club that they formed,
I don't know.
I mean, I remember, you know,
my parents will probably
be shocked to know,
but most of what I did in high school
involved sneaking out,
you know, at night, after-hours.
After, you know-
If you had to get home at 11:00,
you were home at 11, your parents
saw you go to bed, they went to sleep.
You went out some window
and somebody picked you up
and you know, you were out
on some dead-end doing something.
So that was- There was at least two
or three years where that was my life.
And it was sort of required to-
Whenever one was about to have
some sort of life-changing ritual,
it seemed like you would go out
into the woods somewhere to do it.
Whether it was sex or drinking
or just some, you know,
bizarre set of ideas
that were about to occur to you,
you would-
I mean, I found myself walking
into these very strange places
either by myself
or with groups of friends
to have these epiphanies.
You know,
life-changing kinds of occurrences.
So to me, that's just- Was sort of
the sine qua non of this movie,
that they were going to find
themselves out in the woods
in some sort of, you know,
Walpurgisnacht of either drinking
or whatever. So that, I guess,
found its way into the movie.
I can't imagine it without it.
It's not a personal memory
in these scenes.
None of these things happened.
But in a strange way,
all of them happened.
I mean, the atmosphere,
it is more like a dream.
I mean, oddly enough, I got the idea
for this movie while staring at a twig
moving around,
being buffeted in the wind.
And it was-
Don't ask me why,
but that's what it was.
And so somehow these scenes
of the boys running through the woods
toward the cave
and all these sort of spindly, bare trees fit.
You know, it just-
Somehow part of the creative process
or it came out of that process.
I think I have a sort of talismanic scene
in each film subject
that means nothing to anybody else or
wouldn't mean anything to anybody else.
In Dead Poets Society, urn,
the line of description, you know,
says, "They run to the cave
at night from the school
through the forest" or something.
One sentence or something.
And I remember saying
to my assistant director, to Alan:
"Make sure you allow two or three nights
for this line of description. "
He said,
"Well, you wanna make something of it?"
I said, "Yes. It really means
a great deal to me. "
And in my mind,
I used to see them running,
you know, as it were,
sort of back through time, you know.
In my mind, they were running
through history, back through history,
back to the pasts
of all the secret societies,
through Indians and caves and rituals
and secrets and buried things,
and the smell of mildew and damp.
I could smell it.
That's why I wanted them
to have jackets, you know.
That led me to say to Wardrobe,
"I'd like them to have hoods," you know?
They seemed to me to be sort of,
you know, like a Masonic group
or any secret group.
And not all secret groups
were necessarily of course
on the wrong side of the law, you know?
You know, horrible Ku Klux Klan images
come to mind.
But in this case for me, it wasn't that,
it was something else.
It was, you know, a brotherhood
or, you know, some sort of oaths.
You know, in other words,
that moment on the plane
where I was flying home
and saw the title,
the Dead Poets Society.
And then they run to a cave. You know,
that was really enough
to make a film about to me in a way.
And Tom had beautifully written it.
Otherwise I'd be still writing it.
But, you know, it was pregnant really
with possibilities, with echoes,
you know, beyond the literal.
"I wanted to live deep
and suck out all the marrow of life. "
I'll second that.
"To put to rout all that was not life,
and not, when I had come to die,
discover that I had not lived. "
And Keating's marked
a bunch of other pages.
All right, intermission.
Dig deep, right here.
The cave was a set.
It was on the stage. Um...
I remember Peter had a little problem
with the design of it.
The first one we saw
wasn't a very good cave.
It was a very rounded,
artificial-looking cave.
And Pete had it rebuilt
and it was a lot better the second time.
We put a little hole in the top
for two reasons basically.
I mean, one, for smoke to get out
when they lit their fires,
and, two, that there'd be
a little excuse for a bit of light.
It's funny, I was really disappointed
in a little way about the fire
as a lighting thing because
I used it to light from, but we never see it.
In the final edit,
we never ever saw the fire.
And we saw some little sparks
coming up
and I got very excited because
I went to the Special Effects-
And you know, sometimes
movie fires are gas fires,
and they have no sparks.
They make no noise
and that's why they're movie fires.
But I hate them for that.
You know,
I would really love to see sparks.
And I went to the Special Effects guy
and-
To this day,
I can't remember what he used,
but he said, "I can do that. "
He said, "Look, you know,
I can throw this into the fire,
and all these lovely sparks
would come up. "
And I was very disappointed
because we threw those in
and we had those going.
And I thought, you know,
"This is fantastic.
I'm getting sparks for the first time
in my life on a movie fire. "
But it did happen.
The accident happened, you know.
One of the actors
got a little spark in his eye
and of course we had to go
without the sparks.
So after that, in the scene,
I always feel sort of a little bit
that something's missing,
that we never see the fire.
And of course when the sparks went,
we don't get the spark effect either.
All we got was the lighting effect
on them.
So a little disappointed there.
But the scene now that was fairly,
once again,
I hope realistically approached,
that the fire was the main light
in there at night.
And then
a little bit of moonlight there to—
Coming through that little hole in the roof
and maybe from the door
or the opening of the cave.
But otherwise
it was a good little breakaway cave.
We had little breakaway walls and we
could get the cameras at certain angles.
And of course it was nice and warm
on the stage.
It worked out well.
Well overall, I think.
They did a lot of tests, you know?
It was remarkably hard to get it
as something natural,
as to the level they got it.
You know,
they worked very hard on that.
And it was something
that was flagged right from the beginning
as being, you know-
Boy, you know, film history
is littered with bad caves.
I think you could write a book about it
that no one would buy.
But you could write a book
about the bad caves.
And it's very hard
to get anything natural.
You know,
to make a fake tree is pretty hard.
So they got it right. John lit it beautifully.
Then the scenics came in, you know,
doing tests
to get the moss right and the kind of,
you know, presence of water
and, you know, the dampness.
Then I saw the Congo
Creeping through the black
I still got it. You know,
I crated it up and took it back to Sydney.
I often go down there
and play my sax and smoke pot.
Then I saw the Congo
Creeping through the black
Cutting through the forest
With a golden track.
Then I saw the Congo
Creeping through the black
Cutting through the forest
With a golden track.
Then I saw the Congo
Creeping through the black
Cutting through the forest
With a golden track.
Then I saw the Congo
Creeping through the black
Cutting through the forest
With a golden track.
Then I saw the Congo
Creeping through the black
Cutting through the forest
With a golden track.
Then I saw the Congo
Creeping through the black
Cutting through the forest
With a golden track.
Take it, Meeks. Take it away.
Cutting through the forest
With a golden track.
Then I saw the Congo
creeping through the black
At some point, we both agree,
or I suggested to Robin, I think, that:
"Why don't we just have-?
Give you the class one day,
and so at least we've got that in the can. "
And ran two cameras on it.
Over lunch we worked out-
It was an afternoon I think.
We worked out what to do.
We got bunches of books
and things, poetry books
and all kinds of things,
we're looking through.
So we found some Shakespeare.
So he should do something
on Shakespeare.
We're looking through some plays
and things.
And then Dickens.
But he didn't have time
to prepare anything.
He just glanced at headings and things,
so...
You know, it's part of
that remarkable talent of his that he can-
He's a kind of writer, really,
without a pen, you know?
He just writes in the air.
We 're gonna talk about Shakespeare
as someone who writes
something very interesting.
Now, many of you have seen Shakespeare
done very much like this:
O, Titus, bring your friend hither.
In the end, you know,
I said, "Well, I think there's some-
You know, some real nuggets in there. "
So we did take them,
put them into the film.
And I was a bit bothered that
it's used so-
It is used so much in the publicity material
but that- Fair enough.
There was just one day in which,
you know, Mr. Keating let rip.
The most important thing that I think
he got out of Robin
through those improvisations
was that he put Robin at ease
with teaching.
You know, because by improvising,
and not having any text,
Robin had to feel what it was like
to come in and connect with those boys
and entertain them
and teach them something and-
So I think it's fitting
that they end up in the film,
those improvisations end up
in the movie.
Why do I stand up here? Anybody?
- To feel taller.
- No.
Thank you for playing, Mr. Dalton.
/ stand upon my desk to remind myself
that we must constantly look at things
in a different way.
This scene was here too,
and it was a good thing
that that opening got cut,
because it would have been
the third time at the end
as opposed to the second and-
Come see for yourselves. Come on.
I think as a writer at that time,
I would have probably
been overdoing it anyway.
I probably thought,
"We have to have them stand four times
to make the ending mark," you know?
But it— Less is more.
And Peter, you know, being who he is,
was well aware of that,
and I think one of the things we did
in the early parts
of the revisions process
was to beat all the repetition out.
You know, no rep- As little as possible,
because the audience
just gets it the first time.
They don't need to have things repeated
to understand things.
So since then I've-
You know, having had that experience
and seeing it work the way it did,
I just thought, "I'm gonna take that
as the law," you know?
Now, in addition to your essays,
/ would like you to compose a poem
of your own. An original work.
I love sound. I love-
I think whether it's just that much
or whether it was the growing up, it was-
You know, television didn't come
till I was 12 in Sydney.
So radio, you know.
We'd always have one of-
A sort of a large radio
and a hi-fi set
sort of in one big cabinet,
pretentious-looking cabinet.
And I think the bottom section
was empty, you know?
But I think you were meant
to put your LPs there.
But it was empty in our house
because we didn't have any.
And then my favorite radio shows,
I would lie down on the floor
and sort of put my upper part
inside the cupboard. I opened the door.
Well, it made such a great sound box.
To lie there with your favorite serial
or The Goon Show or something.
And, you know,
it would sort of reverberate, you know?
And I used to love plays and mysteries,
and of course, you know,
they'd do all that, do the sound of shoes
on a gravel path, you know.
Rain dripping, you know,
onto leaves. You know, the wind.
The creakings of all kind
for ghost stories.
You know,
so I think I picked all of that up
on what used to be the Caltex Theatre
or something on Sunday night.
And mystery shows,
which were very popular.
So when I'm approaching a soundtrack
now with a good sound designer
as one, you know, arranges,
what a fresh field it is.
You know, what an interesting,
interesting and important field.
You can influence the audience.
You can suggest and hint at things
beyond the corners of the frame,
if relevant.
Certainly with any kind of mood
that you're building, of eeriness
or tension.
I'm gonna act.
Aha!
Yes, yes, I'm gonna be an actor.
Ever since I can remember,
I've wanted to try this.
/ even tried to go to summer stock
auditions last year...
By the time I actually wrote the first draft,
I knew where, what-
Everything that was gonna happen.
I completely outlined the whole piece.
But I think I— You know,
I was a young writer back then
so I don't think I really-
Once I had it all outlined,
it wasn't a matter of aiming it so much.
It was just writing each scene
to be true to what each scene
needed to be.
Keeping the characters consistent,
watching their growth.
So they hopefully grow
through their changes,
their so-called arcs change.
And then just dealing with it moment
to moment, starting at the beginning.
So it-
I think that if you keep the ending
in your mind too much while you're writing,
it's gonna be hard
to write anything truthfully, you know,
at the moment,
or write any scene properly
because you're simply gonna be-
You will telegraph things then.
So for me, the Neil suicide
was sort of preordained
in the sense that he had a father
who was going to repress him,
suppress him,
keep him from being
who he wanted to be, you know?
All that was required of Neil is that
he be very enthusiastic about something
and be the kind of person who,
because of that enthusiasm,
was too impatient to wait, you know?
I mean, then desperation sets in.
And if his father
is sufficiently unyielding,
then I think suicide becomes,
in a sense, the only answer.
The only way out.
- this concern,
but I'm not like you, all right?
You say things and people listen.
- I'm not like that.
- Don't you think you could be?
No. I-
I don't look at Neil as really flawed.
I think he's just-
It's youthful enthusiasm that-
I mean, I can remember as-
I broke my leg my senior year
in high school.
And they first told me
I was only gonna be in the hospital,
which would've been great-
They said, "You're gonna be
in the hospital three weeks. "
And I remember feeling like
that was literally a lifetime.
You know, as it turned out,
I was there six months.
But- And they were just kind of
letting me down easy but-
And I think it's a bit of
the same thing with Neil, you know.
He just- The notion that he would
have to wait another year or two
to go out on his own,
or maybe even four years,
to sort of revisit this acting thing
just seems impossible to handle.
So I don't see it as a character flaw,
but if it works that way,
if it helps us believe
that this is the kind of kid
who would in fact commit suicide,
then I suppose that's useful.
Whoo.
Cannon does literally
cut the film in his mind
as he's reading it in prep, say,
or when he's actually shooting.
And if you throw him an idea,
he has this wonderful habit
of throwing his head forward
and thinking, and you can
literally hear a Moviola running.
And the Moviola's
running the film for him.
Scenes that he hasn't even shot
he will run
because he's balancing your idea
in that particular scene
with all the scenes around it.
He's very conscious of the rhythm
and the flow of the film.
And I think that by doing that,
it means that he can analyze
where he's going, what he's got
and include that in the rhythm
and the flow of the final result.
And it's quite wonderful
because you can-
When you throw him an idea,
he goes into his Moviola mode
and runs the film.
And it's quite wonderful
because he can be silent
for a long time.
In the early days, I used to think,
"Oh, he hasn't understood what I've said. "
But he is. He's actually running the idea.
And he will come up
with this wonderfully logical answer like:
"It's a great idea but if I use that now,
I've blown it two scenes from now,
I've blown the cover.
And I need to hold back on that.
And it's a lovely idea
but I can't use it at this moment. "
And you know why.
And he explains why.
I think that's very wonderful to a technician
who's possibly trying to keep up with him
as far as the ideas for the film
are concerned.
For me,
sport is actually a chance for us
to have other human beings
push us to excel.
In my high school,
you did a different sport each semester.
Or each quarter, I think.
So in the fall I did football
and in the winter I did soccer.
And so, you know,
soccer just naturally fit
with this whole idea
of reading these bits of the poem
and kicking the ball to it.
I don't know where-
Why that occurred to me.
But part of what you have to do
when you write
is sort of give yourself over
to the stream of consciousness that's-
I mean, I consider writing a little bit
like being on the psychiatric couch.
You lie down and, you know, there's-
You don't see the psychiatrist,
you start talking,
and your mind just wanders.
And pretty soon you find out
what's important to you and what's not.
And what's bothering you, what's not.
What are the sort of key moments
in your life?
And it's the same with writing.
You find out- You sort of—
Someone said,
maybe it was Dorothy Parker:
"I write to find out what I think,"
and that's-
You know, I guess I ramble,
I look at twigs.
I— You know, I have these experiences,
and they-
I start writing and then at some point,
my brain organizes them
and they become
hopefully more coherent.
But until that time,
they're just a part of
a sort of dream-like consciousness
that has-
That may have something to say.
And if I trust it long enough,
you know, it will come out hopefully.
Charlie, I got it.
- Congratulations.
- Good for you, Neil. Good for you.
Okay, okay, okay.
Well, everything-
It's terribly important
to keep your flame alive, I think.
It's very fragile,
your motivation.
If you wanna have a long career...
Or you're lucky enough
to have a long career.
And in my case, I take my precautions.
You know, however conscious
or unconscious they are.
You know, I try to keep myself-
I don't say clean.
If I say clean, it sounds odd.
I mean, probably clean
in the nuclear sense,
you know, to kind of remove radiation
off my body.
And to do that, I— You know,
I try and have a life outside of film.
I try and- I try and read a lot.
And, you know, much as I love movies,
I'll go all the time,
but, you know, to listen to music.
And I think in my case,
I prefer to live outside
of the film community.
So I happen to be in Sydney,
north of the city.
I have friends who are in the business,
of course.
But I find that all of this
helps me keep the enthusiasm
that I had when I first started.
Because I saw fairly early on
that you could come to hate filmmaking.
You could come to hate the process.
It's very difficult and, you know,
you do clash with people and you have,
you know, all kinds of sort of intensified
emotional experiences.
You know, you could just
get bored with it.
So I realized, you know,
this was my, you know, determination
not to kill the golden goose.
It's funny to say "the golden goose. "
I used to think, living in Australia,
that I was like Jack, you know.
With a farm and an ax
and a huge beanstalk that I'd climb up,
and I found this castle,
which was not so much-
And the giant,
not so much Hollywood as filmmaking.
So I could go up there
and I could play the lyre
and the giant would give me a golden egg
every now and again, you know?
And I'd go back down to the farm.
And I've always got the ax ready,
you know, but I've never cut it down.
But somehow going between
the palace and the farm keeps me
mentally or creatively fit.
People go to the gym, but I think
it's better to go to the creative gym
in a way.
The body can take care of itself.
Congratulations, Mr. Hopkins.
You have the first poem to ever have
a negative score on the Pritchard scale.
We 're not laughing at you,
we're laughing near you.
/ don't mind that your poem
had a simple theme.
The most beautiful poetry
can be about simple things
like a cat, or a flower, or rain.
You see, poetry can come from anything
with the stuff of revelation in it.
I knew that when I got to this scene-
Because I can remember
that I had put myself in a box
where I was gonna actually have to write a
poem that would appear to be improvised.
It would have to be good enough
that the class would accept it,
maybe even give the boy
applause for it.
And the teacher would find it amazing.
I remember just being terrified.
You know, this is coming.
I'm gonna have to do this.
And I think I wrote it
in much the same way Todd does it.
I just simply- Just closed my eyes
and just started writing.
And this- I got through it,
I looked and I thought:
"Well, okay, it's- A little work, you know.
Next draft, it might be okay,"
so...
And I remember watching this.
Being obsessed that Ethan
was leaving out a word, "a. "
He was- "The truth is like a blanket
that never leaves your feet. "
He would just leave out-
"Truth, a blanket that never-
Always leaves your feet cold. "
And I kept saying, going up to him
between takes and going:
"Truth is like a blanket. "
He'd go, "Yeah, yeah, yeah. "
And Peter finally turned to me because
I was pacing around worrying about this.
He's going, "What's the problem?"
I said, "This. He's leaving out the letter 'a. '"
He said- I said,
"It's not gonna make any sense that way. "
And he goes,
"Oh, please. Don't be ridiculous. "
And I look back and I realize
it's just the quintessential example
of a writer, you know,
protecting their script, but...
Gotta get in yawping stance.
And his kind of use of
the camera, it was always to serve the idea.
And not for its own sake.
You know, I'd hate to think
that, you know, I use something
for its own sake.
I'm just not from that school
of filmmaking.
And there is a school of that,
and it's okay.
Some stuffs good.
That's to make you very aware
of the camera.
But in this case, yeah, it was a very
self-conscious camera movement,
and I think I did it
because it seemed appropriate.
It seemed like it was time
to shake up my own convention.
It was time for the screen
to give you a feeling of what
was happening between these two,
the man and- The teacher and the pupil.
He was taking the camera in a way.
Robin is taking the camera
and spinning it.
He is saying,
"Let's get this camera off the tripod.
Let's just throw it around here.
Come on. Open up.
Open up, you know.
Let it go. "
It's a kind of violence.
And sometimes, you know, you need to do
it to yourself or someone may shake you.
You know, it's like you say in life,
"I feel like shaking her.
I feel like taking him by the shoulders
and shaking him.
Wake up. "
You know, or something,
whatever it is in life.
And so I think Robin
is dangerously close.
There he's really
on the edge of something.
He knows that boy could be lost
and just sort of retreat
into some kind of neurosis.
And yet he can see how close he is
to come- And senses that the boy
is very talented.
Out of all those kids, he might be
the one that goes on to be- Not Neil.
To be the- To be an artist. Who knows?
And-
And so, anyway, it seemed appropriate
that we got in there, and...
I remember at the time,
you know, watching the dailies
that next night or something, thinking:
"I think it's okay but it's ostentatious. "
It's also sort of the capper
of the emotional note that Todd is on
in class, you know?
It is the high point of the movie.
It's where this boy, for the first time,
finds a voice.
So the need for this kind of celebration
to kind of highlight it,
I think is—
It felt right to me, but...
And I think it is the last montage.
- Attaboy, Pittsie, inhale deeply.
- My dad collects a lot of pipes.
You know,
saying Keating's not really a '60s man.
In the sense,
I don't think he'd be an active member
of the sort of counterculture.
Wherever he goes to. I think
he'd go off to England or something.
But I think the boys
would probably, quite a few of them,
of the Dead Poets, would have
got caught up in the '60s in various ways.
And I think that's reflected
in the cave scene.
You know, where you have really a sort of,
through music,
a hint of the sort of looking back
toward the sort of jazz-beat thing
that they'd have been reading about
and heard on the radio.
And smoking pipes,
which is sort of almost the forerunner
of what will shortly be dope smoking.
And in that same cave,
at that same school as it were,
would have been joints passed around
in a few short years.
You know, which I'm saying
as if it's some advance of civilization,
which I don't really think we can say. "Oh,
in those days then, you smoked tobacco.
Of course, you know, now,
in our caves today,
of course we don't. We smoke joints. "
Chaos screaming, chaos dreaming
Gotta do more, gotta be more.
The reason that all the politics was left out
is it's just absent from our lives
in high school.
That was the case for Peter
and I think for Robin too,
but certainly for me, that we were cut off
from that, you know.
It just was- We were in that world
of our own lives, you know.
And the war and-
By the time I was in high school,
the war in Vietnam was raging.
There was already a national debate.
I was involved in it.
But when I was this age, you know,
or when I was a little bit younger,
it just didn't, you know,
sort of penetrate the bubble
of my concerns with girlfriends,
and, you know, that whole bit.
So I think our sense of this school was
that it had successfully cut these boys off
from the outside world.
I can't take it anymore.
If I don't have Chris, I'm gonna kill myself.
Knoxious, you've gotta calm down.
No, Charlie.
That's just my problem.
I've been calm all my life.
I'm gonna do something about that.
You know, and the romantic part of it,
this Chris and Knox business
really starts to take over
in the movie here.
You know, it's that-
It is very self-involved and,
you're right, it is very sentimental.
But it's also, I believe, true to what being
sort of 15, 16 years old
was like back then.
You know, for most of us.
And there were certainly kids,
and I can remember them,
who were involved in politics.
Even- You know, and aware
of the civil rights movement,
the Free Speech Movement at Berkeley,
the beginning of the anti-war movement,
even when we were 14, 15 years old.
But for better or worse, most of us were
caught up in belonging or not belonging
and our relationship to school
and to each other
and to our love life
and that sort of thing.
So... And I think if you add to that
this school which intentionally-
These kinds of schools
which intentionally-
You know, no TV, no radio.
Nothing that will permit you
to sort of connect with the outside world
and find out what's going on,
that's what you're left with.
You're left with this sort of
sentimental, timeless
kind of growing-up period in your life.
- Okay, thank you.
- Okay, bye.
Thank you. I'll see you. Bye.
У aw pi
I think
we all have the desire to be bubbled.
It would be nice not to have to deal
with the enormity of the troubles
in the world around us, you know.
And there's no escaping it.
We're gonna have to deal with it
at some point in our lives.
But I think that, at least in America
at this time,
and maybe in the '80s too, there was-
And that's, I guess, why people
sort of found the '80s and the '50s
to be so similar, that
there was this isolationist-
Kind of this desire to just,
you know, get rich and enjoy life
and not have to deal with
all the problems of the world.
And I think to some extent,
the Keating character's kind of coming in
and saying:
"There's more out there," you know?
But it's not political.
There's more out there in literature.
There's more out there.
There's more complexity in the world
than you have any idea of.
So he's here to shake things up
that way.
And it's- In its own way,
that's what it may have tapped into.
There it is.
/ don't know, but I've been told
Doing poetry is old
Left, left, left, right, left.
Left, halt.
Thank you, gentlemen.
If you noticed, everyone started off
with their own stride, their own pace.
Right before Neil
performs his play, I believe.
And...
It just- It's been so long.
I'd have to look in a script to remember.
But I think the boys-
It may have been right after this scene.
The boys are taught this lesson
about conformity.
This silly little scene of walking around
in the courtyard.
And then I think
they come to class the next time
and Keating's not there.
And there may have been a scene
where Knox goes to the party
and then they go to see Keating
in the hospital.
"That's baa-d. "
Robert Frost said,
"Two roads diverged in a wood, and I,
/ took the one less traveled by,
and that has made all the difference. "
Now, I want you to find your own walk
right now.
Your own way of striding, pacing.
Any direction, anything you want.
Whether it's proud,
whether it's silly, anything.
Gentlemen, the courtyard is yours.
You don't have to perform,
just make it for yourself.
Mr. Dalton, you be joining us?
Exercising the right not to walk.
Thank you, Mr. Dalton.
You just illustrated the point.
Swim against the stream.
Perhaps the fact that,
you know, they're really
contrary personalities-
Bobby and Ethan
are actually playing the other.
- gave it an edge because
I couldn't have asked for more from them.
I thought they were wonderful separately
and wonderful together.
Again I come back to the thing of,
"Oh, what is my job?"
I stand by the camera.
I've just gotta stop the camera
if it's not believable. It's not credible.
It's not- It's just not right, you know.
Because you've seen it
in your mind's eye.
Or you lived it in the past
or you know it somehow.
And you just have to keep doing it
until it's right or something.
And so those two perfectly fulfilled it.
I mean, they-
The sort of apparent weakness in Todd,
the stuttering
and that kind of failure of nerve
that becomes transmuted
into courage.
Whereas Neil, who is urging him on,
who appears to have the courage,
falters and a crack opens
in his personality
and he becomes the weak one.
So in a sense they get- Both characters
get to play aspects of the other.
Both possess courage
and both possess weakness.
One overcomes it
and one is— Succumbs to it.
So in a sense,
they're the same character in a way.
But, well, you know,
they're only young men
whose personalities
are being formed.
You can go in this way or that.
You know, which way will your life go?
Which quality in you
will form your character?
You know,
hopefully for the better or for the worst,
as it of course, can happen.
Oh, my.
It's what teachers must know.
You know, these are young people
whose personalities are just taking shape.
That's why their job's so critical.
To live deep
And suck out all the marrow of life.
To put to rout all that was not life.
Oh, my God.
I vaguely remember
that there was another scene
with the girls at the cave.
But I can't remember what it was.
There may have been a scene
where Charlie had sex
with one of these girls at the cave.
Or at least it was hinted at, but I—
Maybe it might have been intercut with-
At least in the script,
with the scene at the party,
but it's been so long, I don't remember.
Come on, folks, it's
Friday night. Let's get on with the meeting.
Excuse me.
Guys, I have an announcement to make.
And I had the Keating feeling
as a young man and-
Because then I was going to
head into this, you know, gypsy life.
You know, this filmmaking,
as it happened.
It could have been
something else creative,
but I was that kind of personality,
if it was headed that way, so...
One, I would have joined
the Dead Poets Society, but-
If there'd been one. But two, I was-
In my own mind, was already thinking
along these lines
and finding romance and things.
That's why I understood those boys
so much.
I was heading to be a- I don't know what.
You know, a lawyer or something.
We were all on railway tracks then.
We were postwar babies.
But, Chris-
CHRIS: Make yourself at home.
But I-
Baby, baby
Let's make romance
You know your old-time lover
Hasn't got-
I think this boy that
came in and does the Mutt scene-
He came in and said, "All I wanna do
is be the guy that says 'Mutt. '"
You know, and Peter fell in love with him
right away.
And I think in one version
we had "fucking Mutt. "
That was our- That was the fight
we had with the studio.
But at the end of the day
we didn't need it.
I can't remember what happened there.
- Have some whiskey, pal.
- Yeah.
/ don't really drink-
- To Mutt.
- То Mutt.
To Mutt.
Now, how the hell is old Mutt anyway?
Yeah, what's old Mutter
been up to, huh?
/ don't really know Mutt.
- To the Mighty Mutt.
- To Mighty Mutt.
To Mighty Mutt.
Well, there are really four tracks.
There's Charlie, there's Knox,
there's Todd and there's Neil.
And I think the Todd track,
it can't really go too far
because at this point in the movie,
at least structurally,
because this is-
He's only got one more step to make,
you know.
So his character at this moment
I think we imagine
that he's not a prolific writer,
but he's having some success
writing and expressing himself.
And, uh, Neil too has sort of announced
that he's in this play,
rehearsals are underway, so we are-
You know, there really
almost isn't anything to do
but see Knox,
and whether he's gonna be successful
with Chris.
I mean, that's really
the only thread that's-
That hasn't been addressed
in the movie.
Because I remember going back and forth
on that in my mind when I was writing
as to whether he would-
He and Chris would become an item
or not.
Because everybody else
sort of comes to-
I mean, by the end of the movie,
everybody except Knox
has sort of had a bad time of it,
you know.
Neil's dead and Todd's
being put back in that box.
And Charlie's been thrown out of school
so...
And it's possible that the screen time
that Knox gets with Chris
is kind of subconsciously a way
of putting more hope into the movie.
And it- I don't know.
It's very difficult to sort of look at it,
particularly this far in the distance,
and know why you did anything,
you know.
God help me.
Ooh, baby, you're not mine
Hey, little girl
How's about a date?
It's funny, I just-
The more we talk about it,
the less I know about anything
about my process of writing the movie.
I mean, it all seemed obvious to me
when I was doing it.
But in hindsight, so much of it
is about the unconscious
and just sort of making choices
that you think
are the only choices possible.
But 100 writers
would make 100 different choices.
So it's tricky. A tricky process.
And in the movie business,
it's not like novels where you can just write
and someone else will edit it
and then it's out there, and you don't really
have to understand your own process.
In this business,
they're gonna come at you.
As soon as you turn it in, there are gonna
be questions about everything.
There's nothing you do that someone's
not gonna come up and go:
"Why are we making this this way?"
And you've gotta have an answer.
You know? And it's gotta be contained
in the internal logic of the piece.
But they never ask you sort of
about the external logic of it.
"Why did-?" You know, "Why do they go
to caves as opposed to bars?" You know?
That's just-
That they don't worry about. But...
Well, they wanna know why the-
"Why did you put in that this character
wears this kind of coat as opposed to-?"
And you've gotta know all those things.
"And why does this scene happen here?
Why can't we move the whole ending-?"
I mean, that was-
The studio notes on this script were-
The first set of notes were terrifying.
You know, it was-
That was another part of this process
that was just-
You know, you sell it and then
you don't know what they wanna do.
I even remember saying to my agent,
"They wanna buy it,
but what's their vision of this?"
He goes, "You can't ask.
You don't do it that way. "
I go, "This is my baby. I've suffered
four years trying to get this made. "
And he said, "Sorry, you just have to sell it
and trust that they're buying it.
They're buying it for a reason.
They're gonna do it right. " And then I got-
About a week later, I got about
40 pages of notes saying things like:
"Well, the teacher is the main character
of this piece
but he's really not in it very often
so let's- We need to change this.
Let's start the movie with him
in high school
and watch- And get rid of these kids. "
Blah, blah, blah.
And then it just went on from there.
And I went, "Oh, my God. " You know?
"They're just gutting it.
They don't get it at all. "
And went to the first meeting
at the studio
and there was a group of junior executives
in the room
and myself and Steven Haft
and Jeff Katzenberg.
And Katzenberg was sitting in a chair
kind of going like this with the notes.
Just reading,
almost like he was speed-reading them.
And I went, "Oh, God. " And we just
sat there for minute after minute.
And I thought, "Oh, this-"
Because I was sweating.
I was so angry and conflicted about it.
And the producer said, "Let's-
Should we just listen?"
Katzenberg closed it up and said,
"Who did the notes?"
And one of the executives said,
"Well, it was sort of me and so-and-so.
They're not really polished yet.
I hope they're clear. "
And he goes,
"We're kind of throwing the baby out
with the bathwater, aren't we?"
And they said, "Well-"
And he went- Threw him over his—
Back behind the chair.
And he said,
"Let's just make the movie. "
And started talking about casting,
and that was it.
And they never had a big note
after that.
It was a great moment for me.
Sit.
This week's issue of Welton Honor,
there appeared a profane
and unauthorized article.
Rather than spend my valuable time
ferreting out the guilty persons-
And let me assure you, I will find them.
Norman Lloyd,
I'm grateful that he took the part.
And his experience and background,
quite remarkable
both as an actor and as a director
or producer.
He worked with Orson Welles.
He knew Chaplin well.
Hitch, as he would call him.
Alfred Hitchcock.
He worked as a co-producer
on Hitchcock's Hour.
And appeared in, you know,
countless plays and films.
And is quite an authority
on the interesting and less-discussed side
of Hollywood,
which is— You know, of course,
it's always the glamour.
But on the creative side and on the-
He knew all the artists
and was one himself.
So I very much enjoyed talking
with him.
Yet in no sense does he just,
you know, give you anecdotes.
You have to really, you know,
ask him about things.
Because he's, you know, still a working
actor and very involved in this project,
and had very good and strong views
about the headmaster that he was playing.
And made him real,
yet in an older tradition.
A less subtle tradition of human being.
You know, these were men who have
immense respect in the community
and was shortly about to
go through hell
at those prep schools,
from my research.
Those headmasters-
I mean, for example,
if this headmaster at the school
had stayed on to-
You know, into the late '60s,
he would have probably dropped dead.
I mean, they would have given him
such a hard time
with their student protests
and whatever, so...
That was a very difficult year
and was the end, really,
at colleges and most institutions
of authority incarnate
and the sort of ship's captain
that a headmaster
or headmistress was.
That sort of- You know, they could
have the power of life and death over you.
So he gave that to me,
and he was very much
like teachers that I-
Headmasters that I had known
on the stricter side. There was one I knew
who was a gentler soul.
And I would enjoy any time
that we could get chatting,
you know, off the set about-
About the many productions
he'd been involved with.
You know, and it was really for me.
Tell me about Welles.
You know, tell me about Chaplin.
And I felt connected to a tradition myself
of filmmaking through him.
It's so recent
as an art form.
It's extraordinary
to remind yourself of it.
You know, if you're a sculptor,
you know, you can go crawling
over the ruins of Rome and Egypt.
You know,
and back into the thousands of BCs.
And for filmmaking,
you can probably just at a squeeze
still meet people that worked
in the silent era.
Still alive just.
I certainly did as a young man.
You know, was meeting people who'd
worked in silent movies
and in sound movies.
I'm hearing rumors, John,
about some unorthodox teaching methods
in your classroom.
I'm not saying they've had anything to do
with the Dalton boy's outburst,
but I don't think I have to warn you,
boys his age are very impressionable.
Norman Lloyd, for those who don't know,
is one of the cofounders
of the Mercury Theatre with Orson Welles
and I think produced everything
that the Mercury Theatre did.
You know, Norman is sort of one of the-
And he acted in many productions
at the Mercury Theatre
and many of Orson Welles' movies,
so he's one of our great actors
and producers in the theater.
And I think he brings
that kind of presence to the movie,
you know, as a headmaster.
He sort of has an instant kind of
believability because of
his long history as an actor.
Creak.
He starts walking around
towards my left. Creak.
Creak.
"Assume the position, Mr. Dalton. "
It's all right, gentlemen.
It was odd because
when we were doing the casting,
there really did seem
like there was only one right person
for every part, you know.
There was no other person who could play
the Keating character but Robin
and Norman just-
I mean, everybody else
seemed to either be too harsh
or not of sufficient stature
to play the headmaster,
and so forth.
And the same with the boys.
You know, there was just-
To find someone like Ethan Hawke,
someone who wants to be an actor
who can be-
seemed to be naturally shy on-screen
is just an amazing thing.
I mean, it's so hard.
I mean, most people who wanna be actors
are not shy. You know, so-
And they can't play that, so...
And Ethan has that quality, I think,
that it seems to be really him who's-
And in life, he couldn't be
more the opposite.
He's an outgoing, gregarious,
you know,
kind of rangy guy, so...
Others seemed to-
Weren't interesting in playing that.
Didn't seem to really have the same-
You know, the issues in their soul
that Ethan just emanated.
You know, so...
Or emanated from Ethan, so...
We 're trying to rehearse, okay?
A good persuasion.
Therefore, hear me, Hermia.
Wait, please. Excitement.
I don't hear any excitement about this play.
And take her hand.
Bring her down the stage and stop, and,
"There, gentle Hermia. " Try again.
- What's for dinner?
- Spaghetti and meatballs.
Save some for me.
But, room, fairy! Here comes Oberon.
My sense of Neil's father was the kind
of person who would track you down.
You would not get away.
You know, you would-
You'd stick your thumb out.
You'd end up in a city. And one day,
just at the moment of greatest happiness,
you would be take- Whisked away.
You know, and I think in fact
in the original draft,
and this is something we modified,
that Neil's father did not just wait
in the back of the theater
for Neil to finish that play.
He actually went
into the wings of the play,
and when Neil came off
in the middle of the play,
he said, "You're coming with me. "
And of course,
the teachers producing the play said,
you know, "He's gotta finish the play. "
And he said,
"No, get somebody else to finish. "
So someone else was dressed up
and went out as Puck.
It was that kind of repression
that Neil was dealing with,
that sense that if your father said
"this is the way it's gonna be,"
that that would be the way it is.
So I think that for good reasons,
that was changed in the movie,
but I think that
that quality about his father
and that sense on Neil's part that
that's who his father was remain.
You know, if you think the parents were
over-the-top at the beginning of the movie,
then imagine that scene
and it might have-
I think it was wise
to sort of back it off a little bit.
That was one of the things
Peter and I talked about in Australia
and when he first came
to start preproduction.
And it was,
"We need to change that moment. "
I made a great many sacrifices
to get you here, Neil.
And you will not let me down.
No, sir.
The guy that I based Neil on
was not someone
who committed suicide,
but someone who was
a very close friend of mine
when I was 11, 12, 13,
something like that.
And- Who moved away from my town.
And when I-
He was- Не and I were really close.
And when I finally saw-
And he had a father
very similar to Neil's father,
just terrifying.
I remember spending the night over there,
just being terrified by his dad.
And so stern, so straight.
And when I connected with this guy
maybe 20 years later...
He had been exceptional
at certain things.
And I asked him, you know, "How-?
Are you still doing this? Still doing that?"
And he said, "No. "
I said, "Why not?"
And he said, "My dad made me stop. "
I said, "Why?" He said, "It was getting
in the way of my studies. "
And I just thought, "Oh, my God. "
He was- I mean, so talented.
And I said:
"And, you know,
what are you doing now?"
By then he was doing
something fairly routine.
He had not excelled in studies and had
given up the things he loved in his life.
And I thought, "You know what?
He's- It's like he committed suicide. "
And that was my image
for that character all along.
So, yeah, he was gonna kill himself.
Or his dad was gonna kill him.
Because I love teaching.
/ don't wanna be anywhere else.
You know, I've sort of
stayed close with my high school friends
since high school, really.
And so I don't think they look at me
any different
than they did.
Any differently than they did then.
You know, they've all succeeded
at things too.
So I think we just kind of all
had a sense that,
yeah, this is where we all
expected to end up
and, you know-
Some people I'm not close with,
you know, sort of felt like:
"Was that me in the movie?"
And, "Was that-?"
And it was- That was a peculiar thing
to have people call up and go-
You know, or hear
from the grapevine that so-and-so
thought that some very minor character
was based on them
and go, "My God.
You know, if I've offended somebody,
I'm sorry,
but that's not who I was thinking of, so-"
And either way they were offended.
You know, they were offended
if I used them,
and they were offended if I didn't, so...
That they're counting on me.
He'll just tell me to put it out of my mind
for my own good.
You are not an indentured servant.
If it's not a whim for you,
you prove it to him
by your conviction and your passion.
You show him that,
and if he still doesn't believe you,
well, by then, you'll be out of school
and you can do anything you want.
No.
Just before making Dead Poets Society,
I was standing
in Jeff Katzenberg's office.
It was his project.
He was then at Disney.
And I'd just returned from Europe,
very frustrated.
I'd actually gone to Europe from his office,
where we'd shaken hands
on a little film, a little comedy I'd written
called Green Card.
It was only 75 pages long
and I'd written it for Depardieu.
And I said, "Jeff, will you back me
making this film? Yes or no?"
Handshake, you know.
Because I want to go to Paris
and see Gerard.
"I don't know if he'll do it,
but I wanna be able to say to him,
'I have backing. "'
Jeff said:
"It's unconventional but okay. "
We shook hands in the office.
I flew to Paris, met Gerard.
Gerard said, "I'd like to do the movie. "
And his agent said,
"But have you told Peter, Gerard?"
And I said, "Told me what?" He said:
"Well, Gerard, you know,
you're not available for one year. "
So I said, "Okay, I'll wait for you
since I wrote it for you. "
So I flew back through Jeffs office,
as it were.
And he said, "What are you gonna do
for a year?" I said:
"Well, I don't know. I'll work on the script,
you know, or something.
And I can't really think what to do. "
And he said, "Why don't you do
another film in between?"
And I said,
"Oh, right, this is sort of 1938
and you're gonna give me
an assignment, are you?"
He said, "As a matter of fact, I am.
You know, read this on the plane. "
So halfway across the Pacific-
"What is it? Something boring?"
You know?
And I opened it and the title,
the Dead Poets Society,
immediately intrigued me.
I thought, "What a great title.
What is it?
What are they? Who are they?"
I have to read it to find out.
I think I was back within six weeks.
And shot it in between.
And so it was like 1938 or something-
It was-
What I'd always wanted was to
not spend always a great amount of time
developing the thing.
But, you know, to go and just shoot,
you know, like Mack Sennett did.
With hair and skin of gold
Yeah, yes, I think the oral tradition
is probably, in some ways, more effective
than the written one with films.
I think it's probably, therefore,
as it were, better to tell the story
to somebody.
They call it pitching.
But the trouble with pitching
is that it's really not storytelling.
It's trying to present it
more like a lawyer,
the best case for your project.
So people tend to allude to other films
and so forth.
You know, it's a kind of Butch Cassidy.
You know, that sort of thing.
It's a little On the Waterfront, a little-
You know, it's horrible.
But to really tell the story, as if it was-
You know, "Let me tell you a story.
It was an evening,
you know, in—
I don't know, Uganda, you know.
And the sunsets in Uganda
are remarkable.
Quite distinctive. "
You know, so that's storytelling, isn't it?
You know, it's sort of-
You just have to put yourself there.
So I did develop some of my-
Right from the beginning of making
American films that I would tell the story
to executives. That was Jeff Katzenberg
and the Paramount group at the time.
You know, you can do it
in about 10 minutes.
And it's a very good thing
because you can find holes, actually,
in the narrative that you didn't see
on paper.
You know, you reach a point, to saying-
You could do this with your own children,
which is also a very good storytelling trend
if you're making it up.
"So at this point,
he decides to go back to Los Angeles.
As he puts the key in the door of his house
on that evening,
it suddenly occurs to him
that he should go in by the back door.
For what reason, he had-
To this day, does not know
but he had to go in the back door. "
And I'm thinking,
"I should have a reason
why he goes in the back door. "
You know, that's interesting.
The other part of the brain is saying:
"That's interesting, he goes through
the back door, not the front door,
which is why he discovers
what he discovers.
But why didn't he go through the front door
if he's got his key?
Perhaps I should just have
a little linking scene
or something that's mentioned earlier. "
So very good storytelling.
As much as I think taping a script's
very good.
I live, you know, out of the town.
You know,
so it's an hour drive to the city.
So I'll tape it usually.
Do all the voices.
Like a radio show.
And, you know,
horses I've done, period film.
You know, and you'd
sort of drum on the table.
Drrrum, drrrum. You know, things like-
I open doors. You know: Rrork.
"Come in. " Heh, hen.
I don't literally have the telephone ring.
Yeah, come on, guys.
Chris, you can't be in here.
If they catch you,
we're gonna be in trouble.
- Come on.
- Oh, but it's fine-
Chris.
It's fine for you
to come into my school...?
I had another film pressing hard
on the back of Dead Poets Society.
As I mentioned though, I had
to wait a year for Gerard Depardieu
and-
You know, Jeff gave me this film
to make in the meantime,
which I thought was ridiculous
that I would like.
It was a joke, you know.
I read hundreds of scripts, you know.
And it was the one, I did.
It happened just as he said.
So I made it within that year,
as it were, and we've all finished,
and then had to go on
to what was a commitment.
Wanted to. Gerard was free
and I moved on to Green Card.
Shooting in New York. And in fact, couldn't
get across to the Academy Awards
without stopping shooting.
And felt Tom Schulman
represented us there.
And...
Then come with me.
... Robin.
And so we were watching it on TV.
A lot of the boys came,
a lot of the poets.
We watched it in New York.
You come with me tonight,
then if you don't wanna see me again,
I swear, I'll bow out.
You know what would happen
if Chet found out?
He won't know anything.
We'll sit in the back and sneak away
as soon as it's over.
And I suppose you would promise
that this would be the end of it.
Dead Poets' honor.
What is that?
My word.
You are so infuriating.
- Hey, there he is.
- Hey, hey, hey.
It's funny
because I had been back in Los Angeles
and when I flew back to Delaware,
they had shifted into nights
and they were doing this scene.
And I remember walking
into the theater.
Peter was as exhausted
as I've ever seen a human being,
looked just scary exhausted.
You know, walking
but with his eyes almost closed
while he was walking around.
And they were struggling
to put this little play,
the Midsummer Night's Dream up,
and Peter walked up to me and said,
"Oh, Tom, Tom, glad you're back.
By the way, they just sent this-
Your script to this place
called Barbara's Place
where they retyped it
and apparently, it's not 130 pages long.
It's 170 pages long.
So we're gonna have to take 40 pages
out of the script. "
And I said, "Peter, we're two-thirds
of the way through shooting.
I mean, if we're gonna take 40 pages out-
We barely have 40 pages left to shoot. "
And he goes,
"I know. Well, you figure it out
and let me know what to do and I'll-"
And then he just laid down on the floor
and fell asleep.
And I thought, "Okay, this is fine.
When he's awake, it'll be all right. "
Then I heard somebody,
"Peter, we're ready to shoot. "
And he kind of woke up,
just jumped up right away
and said, "Oh, okay, you over there
and you'd move here.
So-and-so, would you like to-?"
You know, he just woke
out of a dead sleep directing.
It was great.
And he put the scene up and it worked.
And then he kind of sat back in the chair
and his head fell back
and he fell back to sleep.
And I thought, "This is just the greatest.
You know, the nightmare of directing. "
But literally just, you know, almost
directing in his sleep, I suppose.
Amen, amen, to that fair prayer, say I;
Neil. That's your cue, Neil.
Come on, Neil.
The days
that I was on the set, we would shoot
and then we'd go back to his trailer
at 5, 6:00 in the evening
and there would be all these messages
from the studio about various things.
The Legal Department needs this
and so forth and so on.
And absolutely, they would-
Someone would have done that
and realized that the script-
Because I cheated
on the length of the script
when I got done with it.
By my computer's calculations,
it was about 150 pages.
I knew that was unacceptable so I just
thought, "Well, I can squeeze it down. "
So I just went through
and took as many words out as I could
and crushed it all together,
and then forgot about it.
You know, and-
So years later,
when people thought-
I think I got it down to 129 pages,
that length that wouldn't,
you know, set off the alarm bells.
And as we did rewrites,
it ballooned up to 130, 135.
But it was never a real problem.
But had they known
that it was actually 150,
or by what he said, 170 pages,
they would have just reamed us.
They would-
Before they started shooting,
they would have said, "Sit down
and take 50 pages out of the script. "
And see whole scenes that we wanted
to shoot would have just gone.
So to a certain extent,
we were lucky that no one checked
until about halfway through the production.
And they may have checked because,
you know, the days were running longer.
Who knows? I have no idea why,
but it happened, so...
I think nowadays, they would check.
They would check
before you started shooting.
And so I think studios have become
much more page-conscious now
than they used to be
because pages are money.
Else the Puck a liar call;
The first cut of the movie was terrifying.
I didn't see that cut.
Peter called me from Australia
and said, "Well, it's 2:46."
And I said, "Okay. "
And then overnight, I thought,
"Okay, he can cut this scene.
That's six minutes.
And this scene and this scene. "
And I called in the next day
and I said, "I have three scenes. "
He said, "This one? This one?"
I said, "Yup. "
He said, "That's the ones. They're out. "
So that got it down to about 2:16
or something,
and some little trims, and that was it,
you know?
They were two of the scenes
that I had to beg him to shoot anyway,
so it was-
I knew they were going out.
The boys getting their assignments.
There's the scene of the-
The waterfall and then the one other.
What was the other one?
Oh, and then the scene where-
There were two classroom scenes
that I think were cut.
One where Keating teaches the boys
to review the book
that they have never read.
And one other,
a really quick one.
Kind of in the same vein.
Well, the scene where he teaches them
how to review the books
is about eight or nine minutes long.
I mean, that requires some-
You have to know enough about the book
that you haven't read,
that they haven't read
to understand how it happens.
So it's a— You know, it's a lot of scene.
It's too much scene.
The waterfall was probably
about six or eight, 10 minutes.
And then the scene- The first early scene
was about seven, eight minutes.
And then there were little trims
here and there that got it down.
Excuse me, please. Excuse me.
- Excuse me, please.
- Neil. Neil.
- Neil.
- We love you, wait.
- / can't, guys.
- Neil.
- Excuse me.
Neil. Neil. You have the gift.
What a performance.
You left even me speechless.
- You have to stay-
PERRY: Get in the car.
Keating, you stay away from my son.
Neil. Neil. Mr. Perry, come on.
Don't make it any worse than it is.
Is it okay if we walk back?
Captain?
Knox.
- ВО У 2: We'll be home about 11:30 still.
- I know where he gets it.
I worked very hard to make sure
this film did not in any sense
condone the suicide.
Rang a psychiatrist, discussed it,
sent the script.
And I said, "How can I make it clear
that this is his decision
and that it's wrong?"
So, you know, I would never like
to think someone killed themselves
if they saw it and were
in a similar mood as this boy.
The psychiatrist said, "Yes, you must do
one thing. You must show his weakness.
You must show that. You must be clearer
than you've got it in the script
that the father when he asks him
to speak:
Tell me what you're thinking,'
that the boy is too weak to reply. "
And so I framed the camera up highish
and had Neil sit into his chair,
as you see him
do in the scene.
And he looks weak,
and I asked him to do that
which he did very effectively.
And looks to Mom. Mommy.
He's not a strong man.
He's not- He can't- He's got a flaw.
And the father's exasperated by it,
which is awful.
You know, the father's, I don't think cruel.
He's just an old-fashioned type of father.
You know, my father was like that.
Fathers were like that in the '50s.
These men had been to war.
You know, they'd shot people
and been in bombing runs.
Whatever. They had seen terrible things
and they thought their children
should be grateful
for what they were giving them,
education.
Is it more of this-?
This acting business?
Because you can forget that.
What?
Nothing.
The suicide scene
and the whole sequence leading up to it
was meant to be-
Was written to be intercut
with a sequence where
Keating leads the other boys
in a walk through the woods.
And... Sort of in a celebration
of the theater that night,
for Neil's triumph in the theater
and Knox's newfound success with Chris,
the girl he's in love with, and so forth.
And it just-
It may have worked on the page,
I'm not sure, but it certainly didn't work
in the movie and it-
And I think we also-
There was a frozen waterfall
in that sequence
which turned out not looking
quite as good.
The frozen ice turned yellow
so it was an unpleasant-looking
frozen waterfall.
So for various reasons,
that scene was cut out.
And so what we're left with
is this sequence of Neil with his parents
and then the suicide.
And I think the whole
sort of style of it, the visuals of it,
the crown of thorns,
which came from the character of Puck
onstage
but of course,
has the obvious Christ reference too,
all came from Peter in the business
of the slow motion.
And not hearing the shot
and then his father just seeing that smoke
next to the desk
versus him seeing the body,
I think was again, all Peter's stuff,
and just worked great, I thought.
Just more shocking
than if you'd seen these things
in a much more conventional way.
Yes, there was a big scene
on the frozen waterfall.
And we went to great trouble to-
Special effects.
To, you know, make it look like
it was frozen, ice frozen.
It's always intriguing
to see frozen water, I think.
And Keating led them in a meeting
of the Dead Poets Society after Neil's-
After his father had taken him away
at the end of the play.
But it was
not believable
and it was wrong to bring Keating
that closely in association with him.
I mean, there's a lot I could say
about Keating.
There's another scene I shot
which I just couldn't get working.
Keating was devastated
by the death of Neil.
And I felt that
all his interest in the Dead Poets Society,
all his way of teaching was gone.
It would take him years to come back to it,
if he ever did.
The only thing that is of great help
to that man
is that the boys stand up for him.
I think without that, he could be,
you know, in some ways,
you know,
headed for pretty severe depression.
Because he would blame himself.
He was a sensitive man.
So I did expand it a bit.
We just quickly wrote a scene
and I had Robin do it there with Mac,
the other teacher,
in which Robin talks about,
you know, the fact that this creativity
that he had in the classroom
has really caused the death maybe
of this boy.
And he felt responsible. And of course
he's reassured by the other teacher.
"There are suicides at school,"
he says. "It happens all the time.
Everyone's been at schools
where there's been a suicide. "
And generally,
they're rather tragically,
seemingly things that could have been
sorted out, you know.
If only- If only they'd talked, you know.
If only I could have helped him, but...
So don't blame yourself.
But anyway, so you-
I really asked Robin
and Robin understood
to play this heavily weighed down,
blaming himself.
And then when he says to the boys
at the end of the film:
"Thank you, boys. Thank you"
to their gesture,
he really means, "Thank you
for giving me a reason to go on. "
And so anything
that was going to deflect that truth,
anything with him meeting them
and so on was really wrong
because it was complicit.
He wasn't a revolutionary.
He wasn't а '60s man, Keating.
He's a much older man, really.
A much older type of teacher.
Maybe a little theatrical but he was-
It was to inspire.
It wasn't to change your life
so that you dropped out,
you know, like the '60s.
Or that you were inspired
to go and change society.
It was simply saying, "Whatever you do,
you can enrich your life by opening a book
or going to a play or a film. "
That there's more than the material lives
that we lead.
What is it?
What's wrong?
My defense of the two deaths
was that even though you would never see
the Keating character die,
it in some way prepared you
for Neil's character's death.
And suddenly the boys would have
something else to be dealing with.
You know, a certain kind of conscious
and subconscious preoccupation
with their teacher's mortality.
So that for Neil,
joining his teacher in the afterlife
or at least seeing himself like his teacher
and therefore better prepared for death
would-
Might have made the suicide even,
you know, perhaps more predictable,
but maybe more palatable too.
Peter's point,
and I think it was a good one,
was that if you see those boys stand up
for a man they know is dying,
then it just doesn't have the same power
as if they're standing up for his ideas.
Anybody would stand up for a person
who's sort of got the courage to continue,
struggle with life if they're dying.
But if it's simply because
you believe in what they've taught you,
then it's a whole different thing.
So aside from any other consideration,
I think that was a good reason
to change it.
Todd?
- Todd.
- Oh, Charlie.
What is it?
Neil's dead.
The scene was originally set-
Was originally set in the bathroom.
We'd already done a scene in the
bathroom, so on the way to the location,
Peter turned around, he said:
"Johnny, we gotta set it in the snow"
because it kept snowing.
And I said, "Right on. Let's go. "
So we shot what we could
and without leaving footprints.
But when it came to the scene in the snow
where Ethan Hawke
was being sick in the snow,
we actually set it up and shot it,
and Peter wanted take two.
So we moved the whole camera
and all of the crew forward
10 feet into new snow
and then just said to the boys:
"Run down, do the same thing
in front of the camera.
There's no marks, there's nothing. "
And the boys-
We did it three times, I think.
And it was fantastic.
It was a fantastic thing to do,
to put it in the snow.
And when Ethan finally runs off,
we were able to then
pan him off through-
You know,
and he ran through virgin snow
all the way down to the wharf
on the lake's edge.
And I think it added so much to the film
to be able to put the boys
out into that situation
that had just occurred
on the way to work, basically.
And Peter and the boys, the actors,
were quite ready and prepared to adapt
and just make the best
of what we had there.
And it doesn't matter
what happens in preparation
and all the thinking and anticipation
that you think you can do.
There's always something nice
that happens.
And if, as a crew, say,
and Peter, you know,
is ready, obviously,
and the actors can adapt quickly,
I think you can end up
with some amazing stuff.
I think in every situation
in the making of a movie,
I feel the question has to be asked,
you know:
Where are we doing the next shot
and why?
And that's what I ask myself, you know.
Why is the camera going here
and what size is it?
Because, you know, we all know
that except for the first shot of a film
and the last shot of the film,
every other shot comes out of another
shot and goes into another shot,
so it must flow in the final edit.
And Peter particularly
is very, very aware of that,
apropos of his Moviola in the brain.
And so by trying to bring an emotion
to a scene,
it's very crucial as to where you put
the camera and why.
You know, why is it this far back?
Is it gonna show the empty room?
The boys have gone.
He feels that he's failed.
And that the empty room means that,
you know, it hasn't worked.
His Dead Poets Society
has actually caused more pain
than it should have.
It should have been a beautiful release.
So that, you know,
by showing emptiness around him
and then cutting into the close-up
to then, you know, dot the I on the pain
that he's going through
seemed to be the logical way to do it.
But it's not to say that couldn't have been
a long lens in a different situation.
And I think that it's,
why are you using that lens
to portray or to help enhance
a certain emotional moment?
It is generally decided for each situation
rather than a set.
You know, a 30, a 35 lens might be,
you know, an emotional lens,
say, that does this.
Any lens will do it.
It's how and where you put it.
And how it cuts in to the one in front
and the one behind as a flow.
I must say I'm very conscious
of what's in the background,
what's in the foreground and why.
Some people dress the foreground
for the sake of dressing the foreground.
I don't agree with that.
I think that, you know, the foreground
and the background should be selected.
Therefore deciding on the angle
of the camera
for its background value
to that moment.
It might not have the door in shot
because the door is escape.
It can- It's a way out or it's a way in.
So maybe you'd prefer
not to show the door.
Just move the camera a little bit.
There's a million things
that you could analyze in the frame
either in background or foreground.
You know, and Peter's very interesting
in this way.
- You told him about this meeting?
- Twice.
That's it, guys. We're all fried.
- How do you mean?
- Cameron's a fink.
- He's in Nolan's office right now, finking.
- About what?
I love small spaces.
There's- Often on films, you know, people
will say, "Oh, this room is too small.
We can't shoot in there. "
And I look at it and I think, "Yes, we can. "
Being, I think, a realist cameraman,
I hate taking walls out even though
they're available on a stage set.
Because deep down
I have this feeling that for the actor,
if you take a wall out,
that means it's a set.
And it's not- We're not real anymore.
But even on a stage set,
if you leave the walls in,
somehow I feel that the actor
can then relate to it as being real.
As soon as the wall comes out,
you can see people on set.
You can see, you know,
you're in another room.
And that I feel I like to try and avoid.
I love trying to use the room as the room
and make the camera fit in that room.
Because often as not you'll find
if you can take a wall out,
then you can put the camera
6 feet further back in that room
than it could ever, ever in reality be.
And that gives you angles in the room
that aren't real.
And I feel that in all honesty
that an audience
is aware of perspective.
Whether they could ever explain it to you,
back to you or not, doesn't matter.
I think they're aware of perspective
of a room.
And that if suddenly you put
a wide-angle lens 6 feet through a wall
to get a wide shot in a room,
I honestly believe they subconsciously feel
that's not right.
You couldn't get that.
And therefore it makes it a movie
and takes it out of this reality.
So that I always try and-
Try and shoot movies
so that you're in the room,
the camera is in the room
and therefore the perspective is correct.
And I think in the cave
and in the dorm rooms
of Dead Poets Society,
I think we've gone for that
as much as possible.
Even though, you know,
we did take walls out.
But I still try then to make the camera feel
as though it's inside the room
as a subconscious thing.
It's not outside the room.
And I think that-
I think Peter is very aware of that
and was on Dead Poets Society,
that the whole thing is reality driven.
That the boys are in their space
of that college, of the rooms, of the cave
and even traveling to the cave.
And we tried to keep that
as real as possible,
even though we were using sets.
And I think- As I said,
"You learn something from every film. "
And I think that over the years
I have learned that.
And I feel that it is right
that you have to keep and maintain
that subconscious reality.
But also as I said earlier, I think too
that an actor feels possibly the same.
That when the wall comes out,
it's a set.
But if that wall doesn't come out and
the camera's squashed in the corner,
and the operator's really scrunched
in the corner
trying to get the shot as wide as he can
but it's still within the confines of that area,
and the wall hasn't come out,
it's still a four-walled room,
that the actor then subconsciously,
I really believe, will feel that he's in reality
and can give a performance
that suits that.
So they're only little things.
They're only very small things,
but I think that all those small things
add up so that-
I'm not frightened of it.
In fact, I often push very hard
to convince directors that:
"No, we can make this whole scene
work in this room. " But they-
They may be used to somebody else
who says:
"Oh, no. The wall's gotta come out
and the roof's gotta come off
and this and that and the other thing. "
And suddenly it's not a reality anymore.
It is a set.
So I try to go up against that
as best I can.
- Hello, son.
- Hello, darling.
Mom.
I remember when I was writing it,
trying to decide
whether Todd would sign,
it was painful for me to think
that this kid would have to sign it.
And I think that in several versions,
he didn't sign.
And as I recall though,
it seemed pretty obvious
that if the kids didn't sign,
they wouldn't be in that room,
in that classroom, at the end.
Because if you didn't sign,
you were gonna be expelled.
So I think Peter may have solved it
by not actually seeing Todd sign it.
I think he just cut away
and we know he signed,
but we don't have to go through
the painful experience of watching him
sign that paper.
It describes how your teacher,
Mr. Keating...
The emotion that the viewer contributes
that joins with the emotion coming from
or sentiment from the filmmaker
is the great meeting.
And therefore if you-
Rather than being didactic as a filmmaker,
you know, you simply present
your story,
and then the audience member comes
towards you and forward and joins you,
the experience is greater than you,
you know, could have made it
if you just made a propaganda film.
Selling something,
it's like an advertisement.
You know,
where the film is open enough.
Now, to do that, you're gonna lose
some people. "I don't get what it's about.
It's kind of sort of nothing,
you know?
It was boring. "
But the other person says,
"Oh, no.
That was just that it wasn't hitting you in
the head all the time like a lot of films do. "
You have to think about it.
If you got into it, if you get into the thing,
then you can have
a very rich experience.
And consequently, very small things
can become very big
for the person who is joined to the film,
as you say the moment
that Keating looks out his window
toward the end there
with his career in ruins really.
And his friend down there,
the Latin teacher, Mac, is walking...
Peacock-hacking with a bunch
of young- Younger students.
His job is going on
and he looks up. And the shared
wave between them I think is...
Well, you know, up to the viewer.
But I think you can-
You know, you can imagine both men
and their sentiment.
You can hear what they must have-
Would have said to each other
if they'd had a chance to.
It's redolent with all sorts of things
that are only suggested.
Sit.
Taking the- In my original idea,
we were gonna be forced to attend
this kind of honor court
or tribunal at the school.
And I had imagined each of them
being forced to...
To get up and testify
about what Keating had done
and various things he had taught
the classroom
that sort of went against the grain
of what the school stood for.
And that they would each sort of struggle
somehow to make a statement
to defend their teacher.
And of course, that part of the statement
wouldn't be allowed.
I remember sort of being
with my characters in their pews.
You know,
and watching the proceedings
and watching Keating being sentenced
somehow, you know.
And this was all very vague.
What court would this be?
It wouldn't have any real sort of weight.
And then I remember one of them
just standing up on the pew-
That's how it happened.
He stood up on the pew.
And I thought, "Well, okay.
Now they don't have to say anything.
That's the repeat of that early gesture
that he made. "
So then I quickly moved it into
the classroom and wrote it as it is here,
as it is in the movie.
Gentlemen, turn to page 21
of the introduction.
Mr. Cameron,
read aloud the excellent essay
by Dr. Pritchard...
Yeah, the end scene
where the boys stand
on the desks at the end
and stand up and be counted
for the Robin Williams character,
we set that up in preproduction.
Because Peter wanted to know
where the boys would be
at the end of the film.
And so then we knew
where their desks were
and then we had to go back
and try and work out the entire film
inside the classroom.
That if the boys sat down,
that that's where they would be
in the classroom
for all the other scenes
in the classroom.
So it was a very, very calculated
positioning of the boys within that room
and it all hinged on the end shot,
which I thought was interesting.
It was also interesting in the lighting
that when they did stand up
that Ethan Hawke
was the one who stood up
right beside a practical lamp
that was hanging down.
And it was the gaffer
who raised up to me and he said:
"He's too hot there
but I can pull that back. "
And I said, "No, don't.
Don't do it, Normy.
Because if he's overexposed,
he's the one who caused the shift.
He's the one who changed. "
And so therefore his face is lit very bright
on one side and darker on the other,
and that's the two sides of him.
And Normy was beside himself with worry
until we saw dailies.
And he said, "Oh, no. It looked good. "
And I quite like that.
That when he stood up,
he was the one who had,
you know, the two shades on his face,
light and dark.
О Captain! my Captain!
Sit down, Mr. Anderson.
Do you hear me? Sit down.
Sit down.
The way Robin,
you know, interpreted that last moment
was all his-
I think the only thing I said to him
was to resist the emotion.
I said, "There's a lot of emotion
in this room that you're coming into. "
Because the boys were- I think
we'd shot all their side of it or whatever.
But they were whipped up anyway,
you know. They loved him.
Well, they love Robin.
There's not any other way to put it.
You know, they-
Both as the character and his-
Because of his generosity
during the shoot.
And, you know, laughing
and talking to them and hanging out.
You know, he was-
Whether extras or the key actors.
And he was funny, you know.
You do really admire somebody
who's funny when the humor is not cruel,
which Robin's isn't,
very unusual for that reason.
Anyway, so when Robin came in
to that classroom
for the quick rehearsal we did,
for a very low-key rehearsal-
Just hitched, you know, the marks,
the frame. And so then he did his takes.
And I just said to him, "You know,
just don't let the emotion affect you.
That's the emotion on our movie set. "
You know, in other words:
"Let the audience be moved.
Don't you be moved. "
You know,
"The less is more really from you. "
And he did it just perfectly.
I think that is—
You know, I believed him.
That's all you can ask.
Thank you, boys.
Thank you.
I think that I wrote,
"the close-ups of the boys, blackout. "
So each boy you'd see
standing. It's pretty much like what it is.
And then, you know,
I have to mention the music here,
which I think Maurice Jarre
did a great job with.
This theme that just runs so
sort of subtly through the movie.
It just comes out here at the end.
For me anyway, it was very emotionally,
you know, charged.
Peter also-
I think the temp score-
A lot of the temp score of the movie
was from The Mission,
which I thought was a wonderful score.
And I remember when I saw it
with the temp score,
I just thought, "Oh, my God.
We're never gonna be able to get
anything this good," you know.
And of course,
good old Maurice came through.
But it was hard to-
When I first saw the film
without the temp score
to really adjust to Maurice's score.
But, boy, it really worked for me.
Well, of course,
this presentation of the film
is because of the brilliance
of the director.
I mean, he knew exactly
what he wanted to put on film
in the visuals and in the performance.
It was very interesting
that as he went into postproduction,
as he got closer towards
finishing the final edit,
I rang to find out
how the film was going
and Peter said, "Well, it's going well. "
He said, "But we're a bit long. "
And he said, "I fear we're going to have
to cut it down a little bit. "
And I sort of said, "Well, what do you think
would have to go?"
And he said, "I think maybe the girl
might have to go, the girlfriend. "
He said, "But I don't want to.
I think she's a lovely little sort of catalyst
in there amongst the boys. "
And he said, "I don't wanna lose her. "
When I finally, I think six weeks later,
flew over to do the release print timing,
she was still in the movie.
There was nothing missing.
And I said to Peter, "How did you do it?
How did you get the film down to time?"
He said, "We just nipped away
at every shot.
Just went through the whole movie
and nip, nip, nip.
Two frames here, eight frames there
and just slowly shortened,
tightened everything up in that entire
movie until it came down to length. "
I don't have a favorite scene
in the Dead Poets Society.
But I do have faces.
I do see the faces
of the boys and of Robin
in certain moments and certain lights.
You know, I see Charlie
on the telephone.
You know, and I see Neil
with his eyes blazing with excitement
for his part that he's got, you know?
I see Todd and Robin in that-
Their faces where he's trying-
The poem is stumbling out
and Robin is urging him on.
And I think these are the things I recall
because these are the things I didn't do.
You know, these are things
that were surprises to me
and therefore that's what I recall,
and this is their work.